为何那么久还未到？
Why are we not there yet?
你不要这样，糖吃完就会到
Don't be like that. We'll be there when you finish your candy.
这糖已是第八粒，骗人的
This is already my eighth piece. You tricked me.
爸爸，何时才到？
Dad, when will we get there?
多吃一粒糖
Have another caramel.
转了这个弯，就到了
Once we go around this bend, we'll be there.
这儿的空气很清新
The air here is so fresh.
最适合妈咪养病
It's the perfect place for Mom to recover.
那个是谁
Who's that?
邮差叔叔，一定很快就到
It's the postman. He'll be here in a minute.
邮差叔叔，你好吗！
Hello, Mr. Postman!
我是大卷草子！你好吗？
I'm Kusakabe Satsuki! How do you do?
请多多指教
Pleased to meet you.
次子，坐稳
Mei, hold on tight.
这儿有很多弯角
There are lots of twists and turns here.
好晕呀，好晕呀
I'm so dizzy! So dizzy!
你好，小朋友
Hello there, little one.
你家人在家吗？
Is anyone from your family home?
他们在对面干活
They're working across the road.
多谢你
Thank you.
大家好吗？
How are you, everyone?
我是刚刚搬来的大卷
I'm Kusakabe. We just moved here.
请多多指教
It's a pleasure to meet you.
女儿人家都不害羞
Girls shouldn't be so shy.
和你很熟络吗
Do you know him that well?
多谢你
Thank you.
哈⋯我搔你痒⋯搔你痒⋯哈⋯
Ha… Tickle, tickle… Ha…
我们终于到了
We're finally here.
真好！
This is great!
呀⋯等等我呀⋯
Oh… wait for me…
不用那么心急
Don't be in such a hurry.
这条河好美呀
This river is so beautiful.
是呀！
Yeah!
你见到有鱼吗？
Do you see any fish?
为何我看不见？
Why can't I see them?
你的近视眼，小心戴眼镜呀
You're so nearsighted. Be careful with your glasses.
小心，不要掉下河呀！
Careful! Don't fall into the river!
先看看屋子漂不漂亮
Let's see if the house is pretty first.
让一让，让一让，我先看呀！
Move over, move over! I want to look first!
好漂亮呀，过去看看
It's so pretty. Let's go over there.
哈⋯哈⋯真好！⋯哈⋯
Ha… ha… this is great!… ha…
快点
Hurry up!
那么残旧，像是鬼屋
Looks like a haunted house!
哈！真好
Ha! This is great!
真好！够刺激呀
This is great! It's exciting!
那么儿戏，像是快塌下来
It looks so flimsy, like it could collapse any minute.
真好！
That's great!
次子，你看看那棵树⋯
Mei, look at that tree…
好高好大呀，看看
It's so tall and huge. Look!
爸爸说我们小朋友的成就
Dad says when we grow up,
日后要像这棵树那样
we should become like that tree
那么高大呀！
and grow big and tall!
爸爸呀，这棵是什么树？
Dad, what kind of tree is this?
是橡树！
It's an oak tree!
橡树？
An oak tree?
大笨象变的树吗？
A tree that turned into a big elephant?
小心点！
Watch out!
有粒种子呀！
An acorn!
姐姐，给我看看！
Satsuki, let me see!
不给，不给，不给！
No, no, no!
追到请你吃鸡腿
If you catch me, I'll buy you a chicken leg!
我也找到只鸡腿
I found a drumstick too!
鸡腿？在这里怎会有鸡腿？
Chicken drumsticks? Why would there be chicken drumsticks here?
这些！
These!
我捡到粒种子，爸爸
I found a seed, Daddy.
我也捡到一粒呀
I found one too!
种子？在屋里怎会有种子？
Seeds? How could there be seeds in the house?
是！为何会这样？
Yes! How could that happen?
可能是松鼠搬进来的
Maybe some squirrels moved in.
松鼠懂得搬屋吗？
Do squirrels know how to move house?
先生，这些东西搬到那里？
Sir, where should I put these?
对不起，请搬进来，得罪了
Excuse me, please bring them in. Sorry for the trouble.
快点去打开后门透透气
Hurry and open the back door to let some air in.
乖乖的快点去
Be a good girl and hurry up.
来呀⋯来呀⋯来呀
Come on… come on… come on…
这两个小妹妹，很聪明
These two little girls are very clever.
快点来吧
Come on, hurry up.
追我呀，追我呀
Catch me! Catch me!
哈！⋯来呀⋯来呀⋯来呀⋯
Ha!… Come on… come on… come on…
⋯开！
Open it!
先看看
Let's have a look first.
呀⋯
Ah…
唔，没问题！
Mm, no problem!
爸爸说，见到鬼怪就要靠吓
Dad says if you see ghosts, you have to scare them away.
不见了？
They disappeared?
去了哪儿？
Where'd they go?
不见了？
They disappeared?
去看看
Let's go look.
是嘛，看看还有没有未走的
I see. Let's check if there are any left.
没有！
No!
那边是浴室
The bathroom's over there.
刚才我们见到些鬼怪
We just saw some ghosts.
什么？
What?
那些鬼怪给我们两个吓倒
The two of us scared those ghosts away.
进了浴室那边，现在不见了
They went into the bathroom, and now they're gone.
让我看看
Let me have a look.
见到吗？
Did you see them?
没有，那些只是煤屎
No, those were just soot sprites.
是煤屎，不是鬼怪？
Soot sprites, not ghosts?
你们刚在外面那么光进屋
You came in from that bright sunshine outside,
所以眼花！
so your eyes were playing tricks on you!
告诉你们，当阳光晒进屋
I'm telling you, once the sunlight shines into the house,
什么鬼怪都会跑光的
all the ghosts and goblins run away.
见光就跑的！
They run the second they see the light!
煤炭屎鬼跑了，鬼怪全不见了
The soot sprites ran away, and all the ghosts are gone.
真好⋯哈⋯
That's great… Ha…
你们不要玩了，快点去做事
Stop playing around and get to work.
你们懂得上二楼吗？
Do you know how to get to the second floor?
快上二楼，将所有的窗打开
Hurry upstairs and open all the windows.
是！
Okay!
⋯我要去呀⋯
…I want to go too…
楼梯呀
The stairs!
不是这里
Not here.
没有
Nope.
楼梯呀
The stairs!
在哪儿？
Where are they?
没有的
They aren't here.
没有的，没有的
Not here, not here.
会不会在这儿？
Could they be over here?
喂，找到了
Hey, I found it!
这么黑，会不会又有⋯
It's so dark. Do you think there might be…
煤炭屎？
soot sprites?
什么声音？
What's that sound?
鸡腿？
A drumstick?
煤炭屎鬼跑了
The soot sprites ran away.
用绝招
Use your secret weapon.
这么大胆戏弄我们两个
How dare you tease the two of us like that.
让我应付你
I'll take care of you.
有煤炭屎鬼
There are soot sprites!
次子，快帮手
Mei, come help me!
来呀
Come on.
好重的，小心点
It's heavy. Be careful.
爸爸，爸爸
Dad! Dad!
屋里又有鬼怪
There are ghosts in the house again!
你打开窗就不用怕那些鬼怪
If you open the windows, you won't be scared of ghosts.
爸爸高大威猛，又英明神武
Dad is big and brave, and really amazing too.
糟糕！
Oh no!
真好，我捉到
I got one!
爸爸 救命！
Daddy, help!
姐姐！姐姐！
Satsuki! Satsuki!
真是活泼可爱
You're so lively and adorable.
这位就是住在我们邻家的八婶
This is Granny from next door.
她好好人，快点叫人
She's very kind, so say hello.
八婆，你好吗？
Hello, Granny.
我是草子呀
I'm Satsuki.
草子小姐，你好吗？
Hello, Miss Satsuki.
你们提早搬进来
You moved in earlier than expected.
我没时间帮你们打扫
I didn't have time to help you clean up.
真是不好意思
I'm so sorry.
你太客气了
You're too kind.
大家都是邻居
We're neighbors, after all.
好应该互相帮助的
Of course we should help each other.
次子，你的手为何这么肮脏？
Mei, why are your hands so dirty?
我捉到煤炭屎鬼
I caught a soot sprite.
你看看你的脚
Look at your feet.
为何会这样？
How did they get like that?
原来你们见到煤炭屎鬼
So you two saw soot sprites.
告诉你们，这儿有很多煤炭屎鬼
Let me tell you, there are lots of soot sprites here.
煤炭屎鬼？
Soot sprites?
那些飞来飞去，神出鬼没
The ones that fly around and pop in and out?
真是叫煤炭屎鬼？
They're really called soot sprites?
你不用怕，根据这儿的传说
You don't need to be scared. According to the stories around here,
只有乖的小朋友
only good children
才可以见到煤炭屎鬼的
can see soot sprites.
我小时候，也时常见到它们
When I was little, I used to see them all the time too.
我小时候，比你们还漂亮
When I was little, I was even prettier than you two.
这山区真是很特别
These mountains are a very special place.
煤炭屎鬼是不会伤害小朋友
Soot sprites won't hurt children.
只要你对它们微笑
As long as you smile at them,
它们会帮助你的
they'll help you.
甚至你有什么求它们
If there's anything you ask of them,
它们都会帮你的
they'll help you with that too.
你这样吓它
You'll scare them like that.
它们可能已经飞走了
They've probably flown away already.
我早说不用怕的
See? I told you there was nothing to be scared of.
I told you there was nothing to be scared of.
那么大的煤炭屎鬼，你也不怕
You're not even scared of a soot sprite that big.
你不用吓我
Don't try to scare me.
你半夜不要叫我起来陪你上厕
Then don't wake me up in the middle of the night to go to the bathroom with you.
小朋友，真可爱
What adorable children.
拿些水回来，让我清洁地方
Go bring back some water so I can clean this place up.
好的，八婆
Okay, Granny.
真好，有水玩了
Yay, we get to play with water!
真好
Great!
来吧，快点来吧
Come on, hurry up!
是
Yes, sir!
八婆呀，有水了
Granny, we've got water!
继续打水，不要让它停止
Keep pumping! Don't let it stop!
是
Okay!
祖母⋯
Granny…
原来是你
Oh, it's you.
你来找谁？
Who are you here to see?
我⋯我⋯我⋯我来找祖母的
I-I-I came to see Granny.
你祖母？
Your granny?
拿著
Here, take this.
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
害羞仔
Scaredy-cat.
不要叫我害羞仔
Don't call me a scaredy-cat!
特别在这么丑怪的女孩面前
Especially not in front of such an ugly girl!
真没礼貌
How rude!
你孙子真是害羞，像我小时候
Your grandson is so shy, just like I was when I was little.
他拿来的糯米团，很好屹
The rice cakes he brought are really good.
和妈咪做的那些一样好屹
They're just as good as the ones Mom makes.
那就多吃些
Then have some more.
再见
Goodbye.
多谢你，八婶
Thank you, Granny.
再见，八婆
Goodbye, Granny.
这个地方，每一样东西
This place… everything here
都好像充满生命
feels so full of life.
风吹得像鬼叫，很恐怖
The wind sounds like ghosts howling. It's scary.
傻瓜，风不用怕
Silly, there's nothing to be afraid of. It's only the wind.
八婶说见到怕的东西
Granny says when you see something scary,
对它微笑就没事的
if you smile at it, you'll be all right.
你大笑即是很害怕
If you're laughing that hard, it means you're really scared.
你也怕吗？
Are you scared too?
不要呀，我怕搔痒的
No, don't! I'm ticklish!
踩呀⋯
Pedal!
爸爸继续努力
Keep it up, Dad!
来了，知道吗
Here it comes, okay?
好了，大功告成
All right, that's all done.
我们去探妈咪
We're going to see Mom.
真好
That's great.
去医院探妈咪
We're going to the hospital to see Mom.
来了
Here it comes!
好了，我们起程啦
All right, let's get going.
八婆，你好吗？
Granny, how are you?
八婶，我们出去
Granny, we're heading out.
你们去哪儿？
Where are you going?
我们去医院探妈咪
We're going to visit Mom in the hospital.
问医生她何时可以出院
To ask the doctor when she can leave
回家休养？
and come home to rest?
好，再见
All right, goodbye.
那儿呀
Over there!
爸爸，那儿就是医院了
Daddy, that's the hospital.
姨姨，你好吗？
Hello, Auntie. How are you?
来探妈咪
We came to visit Mom.
妈咪
Mom!
次子，你乖吗？
Mei, have you been good?
爸爸说我此姐姐乖
Dad says Satsuki and I have been good.
真的？草子
Really, Satsuki?
妈咪，你精神很好
Mom, you look really well.
是吗？
Do I?
爸爸和医生商量你出院的事
Dad's talking to the doctor about when you can leave the hospital.
是呀，我就快可以出院
Yes, I should be able to leave the hospital soon.
新屋好吗？
How's the new house?
你们执拾好东西吗？
Have you unpacked everything?
傻瓜，不要疑神疑鬼
Silly, don't be so jumpy.
妈咪，你怕煤炭屎鬼吗？
Mom, are you scared of soot sprites?
心里没鬼怪，又怎会见到鬼怪呢
If there's nothing to fear in your heart, then you won't see any ghosts.
是呀
Yeah.
我们希望你的肺炎快点康复
We hope your pneumonia gets better soon
可以回家
so you can come home.
真是那么挂念妈咪
You really miss Mom that much?
是呀
Yeah.
我挂念你多些
I miss you even more.
次子的头发
Mei's hair…
是你帮她梳的吗，草子？
Did you comb it for her, Satsuki?
真棒，有进步
Very nice. You've improved.
不过姐姐时常骂我
But Satsuki always scolds me.
谁叫你不听话
That's because you won't behave.
草子
Satsuki,
过来
come here.
为何将头发剪得那么短？
Why did you cut your hair so short?
我喜欢
I like it.
我也要梳呀
I want mine brushed too!
你等一会儿
Wait a minute.
好了，不要整天争著
All right, stop fussing all the time.
让我帮姐姐梳完才和你梳好吗？
Let me finish brushing Satsuki's hair, then I'll do yours, okay?
我长大之后
When I grow up,
头发是不是和妈咪一样？
will my hair be like yours, Mom?
会，因为你样子像妈咪
It will, because you look like me.
爸爸，妈咪好像康复了很多
Dad, Mom seems a lot better.
是呀，没错
Yes, that's right.
医生说她很快就可以出院回家
The doctor said she'll be able to leave the hospital and come home soon.
是不是明天
Will it be tomorrow?
傻瓜，怎会那么快
Silly, not that soon.
最快也要下星期
The soonest will be next week.
妈咪出院后，我要妈咪抱著我睡
After Mom comes home, I want her to hold me while I sleep.
你不是说你长大了
Didn't you say you were all grown up?
不用人陪你睡觉，忘记了？
That you didn't need anyone to sleep with you anymore, remember?
给我淘气多天都可以嘛
Can't I be naughty for a few more days?
懒惰爸爸，起床啦
Lazy Dad, wake up!
懒惰爸爸，起床啦⋯
Wake up, sleepy Dad…
乱七八糟
What a mess.
我什么都弄好了
I've got everything ready.
我忘记了煮饭给你带回学校
I forgot to make your lunch to take to school.
我已经煮好了，你不用担心
I've already made it, so don't worry.
一阵烧焦味
Something smells burnt.
你乱说，我煮的东西很好吃的
That's not true. What I cook is delicious.
姐姐真棒
Satsuki, you're amazing.
你们真乖
You two are such good girls.
次子，这个饭盒是你的
Mei, this lunch box is yours.
草子，上学啦
Satsuki, it's time for school!
阿信找我
Shin's looking for me.
来了⋯
I'm coming!
这么快就认识到朋友？
You made a friend already?
姐姐很受同学欢迎的
Big sis is really popular at school.
他叫阿信，我上学啦
His name is Shin. I'm off to school!
再见
Bye!
路上要小心呀
Be careful on your way!
早安，阿信
Morning, Shin.
走快些
Hurry up.
迟到了
We're late!
早安⋯
Morning…
爸爸
Dad!
我要出去呀
I'm going out!
记著，不要走那么远
Remember, don't go too far.
知道了
Okay!
爸爸，有午餐吃吗？
Dad, is it lunchtime yet?
刚刚吃完早餐又吃午餐，你傻了
We just finished breakfast. You're silly.
先生，买花吗？
Sir, would you like to buy some flowers?
这些是什么东西？
What are these things?
找水桶盛著它
Put it in a bucket.
有了
There is.
有洞的
It's got a hole in it.
鸡腿？
Chicken?
One mOre　TWO mOre
One more! Two more!
Three mOre　FOUr mOre
Three more! Four more!
很多呀
There are so many!
池池喳⋯
Tweet, tweet…
不要走呀
Don't go!
Bom Bom Bart
池池喳⋯
Chitter chatter…
Bom Bom Bart
池池喳⋯
Chitter chatter…
不要走呀⋯
Don't go…
追呀⋯
Come on, let's chase it…
快走呀，Bom Bom Bart
Come on, Bom Bom Bart!
有只粉红色的怪物在追我们
A pink monster's chasing us!
快点回去主人那儿
Let's hurry back to our master!
我笃
I found you!
好玩呀
This is fun!
好像棉胎那么软的
It's soft, like a fluffy blanket.
你样子好像只大鸡腿呀
You look like a giant drumstick.
你是森林之王龙猫吗？
Are you Totoro, the King of the Forest?
有人没刷牙呀
Somebody didn’t brush their teeth!
龙猫，我叫次子，我很喜欢你
Totoro, my name is Mei. I like you a lot.
我和你做个好朋友
Let's be good friends.
好吗？
Okay?
池池喳⋯
Chit-chat…
Bom Bom Bart⋯
Bom Bom Bart…
就这样，再见
Well then, goodbye.
再见
Goodbye.
我回来了
I'm home!
回来了，原来这么晚了
Welcome back. It's so late already.
次子呢？次子去了哪儿？
Where's Mei? Where did Mei go?
刚才还在外面玩耍
She was just outside playing.
就到晚饭时间
It's already time for dinner.
次子，次子呀
Mei! Mei!
次子
Mei!
次子呀
爸爸，次子的帽子在这儿呀
Dad, Mei's hat is over here!
次子呀，次子
Mei. Mei.
次子起床呀
Mei, wake up!
你怎可以在这儿睡觉？
How can you sleep out here?
大鸡腿
Big drumstick.
大鸡腿？
Big drumstick?
大鸡腿呢？
Where's the big drumstick?
你还在作梦？
Are you still dreaming?
我见到一只好像大鸡腿的的龙猫
I saw a Totoro that looked like a big drumstick.
龙猫，在漫画书里面才有的
Totoro? That's only in picture books.
真是有龙猫的
There really is a Totoro.
它全身都是毛，口是这样的
It was all furry, and its mouth was like this.
有只这么大，有只大些
One was this big, and one was bigger,
有只还更大的在睡觉呀
and there was an even bigger one sleeping.
原来在这儿
There you are.
地方不错，十足基地一样
This is a nice spot. It's just like a hideout.
爸爸呀
Dad,
次子说在这儿见到龙猫
Mei said she saw Totoro here.
龙猫？
Totoro?
来啦⋯
Come on…
等等我
Wait for me!
就在这儿？
Right here?
我刚才看见它在这儿睡觉
I just saw it sleeping here.
但这儿只有一条路
But there's only one path here.
次子，回来！
Mei, come back!
龙猫呢？
Where's Totoro?
我没撒谎，我真是见到它
I'm not lying. I really saw him.
你们不相信我？
You don't believe me?
次子
Mei,
你们都不相信我
None of you believe me.
爸爸和姐姐都相信你
Daddy and Satsuki both believe you.
你一定会见到这个森林的主人
You must have seen the guardian of this forest.
它叫龙猫
He's called Totoro.
这儿的传说是这样说的
That's what the legend here says.
不是每个小朋友都可见到它的
Not every child gets to see him.
你见到它，是会带来好运的
If you see him, it brings you good luck.
好了，我们不如到附近走走
All right, let's go for a walk nearby.
好呀
Okay!
看看有什么美丽风景
Let's see what beautiful scenery there is.
好呀
Okay!
骑牛牛很好玩
It's fun riding on Daddy's back.
爸爸，快点
Come on, Dad!
次子，你越来越重了
You're getting heavy, Mei…
爸爸，看看那棵橡树
Dad, look at that camphor tree!
好大棵呀
It's huge!
是这棵树了
It's this tree.
是呀
Yeah.
爸爸
Dad!
爸爸，快点
Dad, hurry up!
我在这儿见到龙猫的
I saw Totoro here.
为何洞口不见了？
Why is the hole gone?
是这棵吗？
Was it this tree?
她说洞口不见了
She said the hole disappeared.
不是时常可以看见的
You can't see it all the time.
为什么？为什么见不到
Why? Why can't we see it?
乡下人说，不是时常见到的
People in the country say you can't see it all the time.
除非⋯好运气的人
Only the lucky ones can…
爸爸自小在这个森林长大
Daddy grew up in this forest when he was little.
好挂念这儿
I've missed it so much.
希望妈妈她在这儿养病
I hope Mom can rest here and get well soon.
早点康复
Get better soon.
这个大森林，充满了灵气
This big forest is full of spirit.
我们好好的在这儿生活
If we live well here,
这儿会为我们带来好运的
it'll bring us good luck.
来吧，和龙猫说再见吧
Come on, let's say goodbye to Totoro.
要回家吃饭
It's time to go home and eat.
次子，你一定会好好运气
Mei, you're sure to have good luck.
你都会见到龙猫的
You'll see Totoro too.
立正
Attention!
我们向龙猫说再见
Let's say goodbye to Totoro.
龙猫，再见
Goodbye, Totoro.
看谁走得快
Let's see who gets there first.
爸爸骗人，等等我
Daddy, that's not fair! Wait for me!
爸爸
Daddy!
快点
Hurry up!
等等我
Wait for me!
妈咪，今天次子见到龙猫
Mom, Mei saw Totoro today,
爸爸说可以带来好运的
and Daddy said he'll bring us good luck.
希望妈咪你都好运，快点康复
Mom, I hope you'll have good luck too and get well soon.
你上学吧，我应付得来的
You go on to school. I can manage by myself.
你要乖呀，再见
Be good, okay? Bye-bye.
再见
Bye-bye.
害羞仔，你还不上学
Shy boy, shouldn't you be off to school?
快了
In a minute!
心思不集中
Pay attention.
次子，山吹老师
Mei, Miss Yamanuki.
什么事？
What is it?
我妹妹在外面
My little sister's outside.
她妹妹⋯
Her little sister…
看看⋯
Let's see…
八婆，她什么事
Granny, what's wrong with her?
次子她早上发脾气
Mei had a tantrum this morning.
要来找姐姐一同上课
She insisted on coming to class with her sister.
次子
Mei.
你也知道爸爸今天要回大学
You know Dad has to go back to the university today.
你应该乖乖的留在八婆家
You should be a good girl and stay at Granny's.
不要胡叫
Don't make a fuss.
我还有两课要上
I still have two classes left.
而且八婆也很忙
And Granny is very busy too.
是否次子也想上学读书？
Does Mei want to come to school too?
好吧，八婆，我和山吹老师说说
All right, Granny. I'll go talk to Mr. Yamabuki.
各位同学，草子妈妈进了医院
Class, Satsuki's mother is in the hospital,
她爸爸又要工作
and her father has to work.
所以她妹妹今天和我们一同上课
So her little sister will be joining us in class today.
是
Yes, ma'am.
你在画什么？
What are you drawing?
是只龙猫
It's Totoro.
你不可以这么嘈吵
You can't be so noisy.
再见，再见
See you later!
我不上课外活动了
I'm not going to club today.
那明天见吧
See you tomorrow, then.
走快一点，快下雨了
Hurry up. It's going to rain.
糟糕，下雨了
Oh no, it's raining.
好大雨
It's pouring.
走快点，快点，次子
Hurry up, Mei!
你真不小心，来吧
You're so clumsy. Come on.
我好棒，跌倒都没哭
I didn't even cry when I fell. Aren't I good?
今次真是麻烦
This really is a problem.
土地公公，求你叫雨快点停止
Dear Lord Guardian, please make the rain stop soon.
你⋯
But…
姐姐，真是走运
That was lucky, wasn't it, Sis?
不过伞子是破的
But this umbrella's got holes in it.
爸爸出去时没拿伞子
Dad went out without his umbrella.
我们去车站接他
Let's go meet him at the station.
都说伞给吹破了，已丢了
I told you, the wind tore my umbrella and I threw it away.
你很喜欢那伞子，怎会丢掉？
You liked that umbrella so much. Why would you throw it away?
都说已经丢掉了
I said I already threw it away.
明天给你买新的
I'll buy you a new one tomorrow.
我不喜欢
I don't want one.
请问有人吗？
Hello?
原来是草子和次子，奶奶
Oh, it's Satsuki and Mei, Granny.
今天真是麻烦你
Sorry to trouble you today.
麻烦？我们没帮过你什么？
Trouble? We didn't help you with anything.
有，害羞仔将伞子借给我们
We did. That shy boy lent us his umbrella.
是吗？
He did?
不用客气，只是破伞子吧
Don't mention it. It's just an old umbrella.
因为当时雨很大
It was raining so hard then.
幸好他将伞子借给我们
It really helped that he lent it to us.
不过弄到他全身湿透
But he got completely soaked.
不要紧
It's all right.
那傻瓜整天都弄得全身湿透
That silly boy comes home soaked all the time anyway.
才回家的
That's how he got home.
你们现在去接爸爸放工？
Are you going to meet your father after work now?
是
Yes.
你真乖
You're such a good girl.
再见
Goodbye.
有客人来过吗？
Did someone come by?
没有
No.
有车到站
The bus is here.
你们乘车吗？
Are you getting on?
好了，开车
All right, drive on.
爸爸没乘这巴士？
Dad wasn't on this bus?
一定是乘下一班
He'll be on the next one for sure.
你不如去八婆家
Why don't you go to Granny's house?
不要
No.
干什么？
What are you doing?
次子，你累吗？
Mei, are you tired?
刚才叫你去八婆家
I told you to go to Granny's a little while ago.
车就快到，你多撑一会儿
The bus will be here soon, so hang in there a little longer.
为何这部车那么久还没到？
Why is this bus taking so long?
我背你
I'll carry you.
龙猫？
Totoro?
你等一会儿
Wait a second.
借给你
You can borrow this.
快点，次子就快掉下来
Hurry, Mei's about to fall off.
是这样做的
You do it like this.
车来了
Here comes the bus!
什么东西？
What is it?
龙猫拿了爸爸的伞子走呀
Totoro took Dad's umbrella!
你们来接我吗？
Did you come to meet me?
爸爸
Dad!
风大雨大，你们都来车站接我
With all this wind and rain, you came all the way to the station for me.
你们真乖
You two are such good girls.
见到了
I saw him!
见到了，终于见到
I saw him! I finally saw him!
龙猫，猫巴士呀
Totoro, and the Catbus!
猫巴士？
The Catbus?
好大的猫巴士呀
The Catbus was huge!
真好，我终于见到龙猫
I'm so glad. I finally got to meet Totoro.
真好
That's wonderful.
真好，龙猫
How wonderful, Totoro.
龙猫原来是这样的
So that's what Totoro looks like.
真好
How wonderful.
少见多怪
You're making a fuss over nothing.
妈咪，我今晚终于见到龙猫
Dear Mom, tonight I finally saw Totoro.
今晚真是不可思议
Tonight was really mysterious.
可以说又可怕又开心
It was scary and fun at the same time.
这龙猫还送了一个
Totoro even gave us
用竹叶包的礼物给我们
a present wrapped in a bamboo leaf.
回家后打开来看看
When we got home and opened it,
原来全部都是橡树的果实
it turned out to be full of acorns.
我们将果实种在后园
So we planted the acorns in the backyard,
希望将来会变成一个橡树森林
hoping that someday it would turn into an oak forest.
但是⋯
But…
等呆了也不发芽
no matter how long we waited, they just wouldn't sprout.
次子每天都望著泥土很失望
Every day Mei would stare at the dirt, looking so disappointed.
都是我第一次见到她失望的表情
It was the first time I'd ever seen her look disappointed,
我心都很不安乐
and it made me feel uneasy too.
快要放暑假，希望你快点康复
Summer vacation is almost here. I hope you get well soon.
你的大女儿，草子
Your eldest daughter, Satsuki.
乖，要关灯
Come on, lights out.
不要
No!
爸爸，明天那些鸡腿会发芽吗？
Dad, will those drumsticks sprout tomorrow?
我怎知道
How should I know?
间龙猫吧，龙猫才知道嘛
Ask Totoro. Totoro would know.
早点睡吧
Go to sleep now.
池池喳⋯
Chit-chat…
Bom Bom Bart⋯
Bom Bom Bart…
喂，次子
Hey, Mei.
Bom Bom Bart⋯
Bom bom bart…
池池喳⋯
Chitty chatter…
他们在干什么？
What are they doing?
不如我们出去看看
Let's go outside and take a look.
真好，成功了
Great, we did it!
真好
Great!
我也去
I'm going too.
等等我呀
Wait for me!
飞原来是这么好玩的
Flying is so much fun!
树呢？
What about the tree?
真棒
We did it!
发芽了
They sprouted!
发出芽了
They've sprouted!
真棒
Wonderful.
真棒⋯发出芽了⋯
Wonderful… They've sprouted…
有人吗？收电报
Anybody home? Telegram!
请问有人吗？
Excuse me, is anybody home?
大卷先生，收电报呀
Mr. Kusakabe, telegram for you!
为何没人的？
No one's home?
八婆
Granny!
是你们
Oh, it's you two.
是呀，次子，你吃粟米吗？
Yes, Mei, would you like some corn?
八婆，我想吃
Granny, I want one.
好
All right.
八婆，这块菜田像个宝山
Granny, this vegetable patch is like a treasure mountain.
是呀，来！休息一会儿
Yes, come on! Let's take a little break.
浸到很冰冻的
They're nice and cold now.
我不客气了
Thanks for the food.
很好屹
It's delicious.
是呀
It sure is.
因为这儿的阳光和泥土都很好
Because the sunshine and the soil here are so good,
所以吃了对身体很有帮助的
they're very good for your body.
那对妈妈的病呢？
Then will it help Mom get better too?
当然有帮助
Of course it will.
吃了八婆种的蔬菜
If she eats Granny's vegetables,
会立即完全康复
she'll be all better in no time.
妈咪星期六就会出院
Mom's coming home on Saturday.
那时候我又可以撒妈咪的娇了
Then I can cuddle up and snuggle with Mom again.
好了
Oh.
终于都可以出院了
So she's finally getting out of the hospital.
她不是真的出院
She's not really being discharged.
星期一还要回去的
She has to go back on Monday.
是给她习惯一下
It's just to help her get used to things.
那要她吃多些这儿的生果和蔬菜
Then she should eat lots of the fruit and vegetables here.
次子摘的粟米要留给妈咪吃
We have to save the corn Mei picked for Mom.
妈咪一定很开心
Mom will be so happy.
你们有电报
You have a telegram.
因为你们家里没有人
Since no one was home,
所以送来我们这儿
they brought it to our place.
是我们的？
For us?
是呀
That's right.
但是爸爸说要迟些才回来
But Dad said he wouldn't be back until later.
打开来看看，可能有急事
You'd better open it, in case it's urgent.
请尽快联络七国山
Please contact Shichikokuyama at once.
是医院寄来的
It's from the hospital.
是妈咪住的那间医院
It's Mom's hospital.
是妈咪，不知道有什么事
It's about Mom. I wonder what's happened.
婆，怎么办？怎样联络？
Granny, what should we do? How do we contact them?
你冷静些，不要紧张
Calm down. Don't panic.
你可以找到你爸爸吗？
Do you know where your dad is?
我知研究室的电话
I know the number for his office.
但是家里没有电话
But we don't have a phone.
害羞仔
You shy boy.
快带她去村长家借电话啦
Hurry and take her to the village headman's house to borrow the phone.
次子，你不要跟姐姐去
Mei, don't go with Satsuki.
次子，你快回去八婆那儿
Mei, hurry back to Granny's!
请帮我接郊区，东京de
Hello, I'd like to make a long-distance call, please.
地方区号码是1382，是
It's to Tokyo 31-1382.
害羞仔，你女朋友真可爱
You shy boy, your girlfriend is so cute.
这儿是⋯考古学研究室吗？
Is this… the archaeology department?
请你叫⋯叫爸爸听⋯
Could I speak to my father…
不是，是大卷先生
No, I mean Mr. Kusakabe.
我是他女儿
I'm his daughter.
草子呀，是
Kusakabe. Yes.
爸爸呀，我是草子
Dad, it's me, Satsuki.
草子，什么事
Satsuki, what is it?
是
Yes.
是医院呀？
Is it from the hospital?
我知道了，我立即打电话去
I understand. I'll call right away.
妈咪有事吗？那怎办，爸爸？
Did something happen to Mom? What are we going to do, Dad?
你放心
Don't worry.
我问完后打电话回来给你
I'll ask them and call you right back.
你在这儿等我一会儿
Wait there for me a little while.
草子，我现在挂线
Satsuki, I'm hanging up now.
村长太太
Madam Mayor,
我可以在这儿等爸爸电话吗
may I wait here for my dad's call?
不要紧，你随便吧
Of course, make yourself at home.
姐姐
Satsuki!
不能给你，粟米是给我妈咪吃的
I can't give it to you. This corn is for my mom.
不可以，我要给妈咪
No, I have to give it to my mom.
姐姐
Satsuki,
次子，妈咪现在的病情不太好
Mei, Mom's condition isn't very good right now.
所以要迟些才可回家？
So she has to come home a little later?
不要
No!
妈咪身体要紧嘛
Mom's health comes first.
你不要发脾气，你越来越不听话
Don't throw a tantrum. You're getting more and more disobedient.
不要
No!
你⋯你想妈咪死吗？
Y-You want Mom to die?
我不要
I don't!
干什么，只不过迟几天才回家
What's gotten into you? She's only coming home a few days later.
你不乖，我不理你
If you won't behave, I'm not talking to you.
你回去吧
You go on back.
姐姐好衰的
Satsuki's so mean.
我替你们收了衣服
I brought in the laundry for you.
不要那么没心机，提起精神
Don't look so glum. Cheer up.
八婆现在帮你们手
Granny's here to help you now.
你爸爸都已经去了医院看她了
Your father's already gone to the hospital to see her.
你妈咪不会有事的
Your mom's going to be fine.
下星期六就会回家
She'll be home next Saturday.
撒谎
That's a lie.
上次又是这样说
That's what they said last time, too.
只是去医院住两天
They said she'd only be in the hospital for two days.
怎知道一住就住这么久
Who knew she'd end up staying so long?
如果她死了，那怎么办？
But what if she dies?
不会的，草子
She won't, Satsuki.
万一妈咪她真是⋯
But what if Mom really…
没事的，你放心吧
Don't worry, it'll be okay.
有个那么可爱的女儿
With such a sweet little daughter,
她又怎舍得死呢
how could she bear to die?
不要哭，八婆在这儿陪你
Don't cry. Granny's here with you.
陪到你爸爸回来，乖啦
I'll stay until your father comes back, all right?
次子
Mei.
Mei!
次子回来了吗？
Did Mei come back?
没有，她还没有回来
No, she still hasn't come back.
奇怪，究竟次子去了哪儿？
That's strange. Where could Mei have gone?
会不会因为我刚才骂过她
Could it be because I scolded her just now
不知道她会不会⋯
I wonder if she…
去了妈咪住的那间医院？
went to the hospital where Mom is?
她怎样去医院？
How could she get to the hospital?
很远的
It's so far away.
她这么小怎懂得乘车去医院
She's so little, how could she know how to get there by bus?
我去找她
I'll go look for her.
害羞呀，快去找你爸爸帮手
Don't be shy, hurry and go get your dad's help.
次子失踪了？
Mei's missing?
次子，糟糕
Mei, oh no.
她时常都会迷失路的
She always gets lost.
次子，次子
Mei, Mei!
伯伯，有事请问你
Excuse me, sir, may I ask you something?
见到有个梳孖辫的小女孩经过吗
Have you seen a little girl with pigtails come by?
她是我妹妹
She's my sister.
不见，我在这儿都大半天
No, I haven't. I've been here most of the day.
不见有小女孩经过
I haven't seen any little girl come by.
究竟去了哪儿？
Where could she have gone?
你不如去其他地方找找
Why don't you look somewhere else?
次子不要有事
Please let Mei be all right.
次子，我不该骂你的
Mei, I shouldn't have scolded you.
你原谅我，你不要有事呀
Please forgive me. Please be all right.
次子
Mei!
停车
Stop!
你神经病，撞死你的
Are you crazy? You could've killed yourself!
我在找妹妹
I'm looking for my sister.
有见过小女孩经过吗？
Have you seen a little girl pass by?
小女孩？
A little girl?
可能去了七国山医院
She may have gone to Shichikokuyama Hospital.
我妹妹只有四岁
My sister is only four years old.
你有留意吗？
Did you happen to notice her?
我们是由七国山来的
We came from Shichikokuyama,
但是沿路上都不见有小女孩经过
but we didn't see any little girl along the way.
是，多谢你们
Yes, thank you very much.
你从哪儿来？
Where did you come from?
由龙猫山来
From Totoro Mountain.
龙猫山？
Totoro Mountain?
你没弄错吧，很远的
You must be mistaken. That's very far away.
这么远，你怎样来？
It's so far. How did you get here?
那你慢慢找吧
Well, good luck finding her.
草子
Satsuki!
害羞仔，找到吗？
Kanta, did you find her?
还没有，里面都没有
Not yet. She's not in there.
爸爸他们在四周寻找
My dad and the others are looking around.
我和你去七国山找吧
I'll go to Shichikokuyama with you.
现在你先回家，好嘛
You go on home first, okay?
次子一定是去医院时
Mei must've
在路上迷了途
gotten lost on the way to the hospital.
他们刚才在河边找到一只鞋子
A little while ago, they found a shoe by the river.
你快去河边看看是不是次子的
Go check by the river and see if it's Mei's!
还没找到
Not yet.
次子，你不要死呀
Mei, don't die!
次子，你千万不要死
Mei, please don't die.
南无阿弥陀佛⋯
Namu Amida Butsu…
在那儿，你们快过去那边打捞
Over there! Hurry and drag that side!
南无阿弥陀佛⋯
Namu Amida Butsu…
草子正赶来
The Kusakabes are on their way.
次子
Mei!
我们找到次子的鞋子
We found Mei's shoe.
这鞋子不是次子的
It's not Mei's.
菩萨有灵，幸好不是次子的
Thank goodness, it wasn't Mei's.
吓死我了
You gave me such a scare.
原来那鞋子不是小孩子的
So that sandal wasn't a child's after all.
不用找了，摆乌龙
You can stop looking. It was all a mistake.
她没有掉进水
She didn't fall into the water.
那就好了⋯
That's a relief…
真是吓死呀⋯
What a scare…
草子，你去哪儿？
Satsuki, where are you going?
求求你们，让我见龙猫
Please, let me see Totoro.
次子迷了途，天就快黑
Mei is lost, and it's getting dark.
但是我们还没找到她
But we still haven't found her.
龙猫
Totoro!
龙猫，次子迷了途
Totoro, Mei is lost.
我老是找不到她
I just can't find her.
求求你，帮我找她
Please, help me find her.
她一定是不知躲在哪儿在哭
I'm sure she's crying somewhere.
我现在都不知道怎么办
I don't know what to do.
原来是只猫巴士
It's a Catbus!
请小心车门
Please watch the doors.
Please Stand　clear of door
Please stand clear of the doors.
次子
Mei.
树都避开
Even the trees are getting out of the way!
次子
Mei!
姐姐呀
Satsuki!
次子
Mei!
姐姐
Satsuki!
傻瓜，我很担心你
You silly girl, I was so worried about you.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你想将粟米送去医院给妈咪吃？
Did you want to take the corn to the hospital for Mom?
你送我们去医院？
You'll take us to the hospital?
真好
That's great!
对不起，因为医生要我提前出院
I'm sorry. The doctor says I can leave the hospital early,
我很心急，所以打电报给你们
so I was so excited, I sent you a telegram.
吓了你们，真不好意思
I'm sorry I gave you such a scare.
如果孩子知道⋯你明天可以出院
If the girls knew you could leave the hospital tomorrow,
我想她们一定很开心
I'm sure they'd be very happy.
她们希望你出院好久了
They've been hoping for you to come home for so long.
我住了医院这么久
I've been in the hospital such a long time,
使她们受了很多苦
and they've had to go through so much.
没人照顾她们，我心里很难过
It breaks my heart not being there to take care of them.
她们很懂事
They're such good girls.
我出院后
Once I'm out of the hospital,
她们两个就不用那么辛苦
those two won't have to work so hard anymore.
不辛苦，她们整天都说
Oh, they don't mind. They're always saying
要找龙猫送药来医好你
they'll find Totoro and have him bring medicine to make you well.
孩子们真是天真
Children really are so innocent.
妈咪好像没事了
Mom looks all better now.
还精神很好
She seems full of energy, too.
是呀
Yeah.
我好像吃了龙猫的药那么精神
I feel so full of energy, like I took Totoro's medicine.
是吗？
Really?
有条粟米，是谁拿来呢？
Who brought this corn here?
莫非她们真的找到龙猫
Maybe they really did find Totoro,
送粟米来给我治病
and brought me this corn to make me well.
我想可能是，你看看
I think maybe they did. Look.
我们最疼你
We love you very much.